Armstead L. Robinson papers MSS 12836
Albert and Shirley Small Special Collections Library
Series 4: Research Materials (Boxes 11-32)is the collection's largest series and contains research materials, 1850-1995, on the American Civil War, African-American history, Robinson's dissertation and Bitter Fruits of Bondage book, and census projects. (His extensive census research is filed at the end of this series). The majority of nineteenth century material are photocopies. Folders are arranged alphabetically, and several contain materials cited in Bitter Fruits of Bondage. Folders of interest include: "First Africans in Virginia (Jamestown)" (Box 11); "Memphis Social History Project/Memphis Leadership Project" (Robinson's letter of June 17, 1977 describes this project as having been conceived by him in 1966, while a junior at Yale, as a history of the Black community in Memphis) (Box 12); "Research Material: Reconstruction: Black Political Leaders in Memphis, Tennessee (city directory and census data)" (Box 14).Census materials comprise the latter part of Series IV, and at twelve boxes are the largest groups of materials in the series and the collection (Boxes 20-32).
Series 5: Writings and Publications (Boxes 32-42)the collection's second largest series, contains Robinson's writings, publications and manuscripts of his Yale honors' thesis, University of Rochester dissertation "Day of Jubilo" [formerly "Cotton, Contrabands, and Mr. Lincoln's War"], Bitter Fruits of Bondage (Boxes 32-38), articles, book reviews, public and conference lectures. These folders are arranged alphabetically by title and chronologically within title headings. Some of Robinson's manuscripts were critiqued on his behalf by colleagues and fellow historians such as Ira Berlin, Edward L. Ayers, Michael F. Holt, Michael Johnson, Julie S. Jones, Theresa M. Towner, and Bell Irvin Wiley.
Series 6: Oversize (Oversize Box U-10) is the last for the collection. Items are arranged chronologically and include: a photostatic copy of a 1863 letter from James Seddon, Confederate secretary of war, to Jefferson Davis; two pencil and ink sketches of Carter G. Woodson; a 1994 certificate declaring Robinson an honorary citizen of Natchez, Mississippi; an incomplete numbered set of "Images of Afro-Americans of the Emancipation Era" (Hodges Publications); University of North Carolina Department of Geography census templates and demographic maps; photostatic copies of Civil War maps from National Archives (Washington, D.C.) record group numbers 77 and 94, and speaking engagement posters.
Slavery--United States--History--19th Century; Slave trade-United States-History; Audiocassettes.; letters (correspondence); African Americans -- Study and teaching; African Americans -- History -- 1863-1877; United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865 -- African Americans
- Correspondence, 1967-1995; 1
  - Correspondence; Black Student Alliance; Yale University, 1964-1995; 1 Cubic Feet 1 c.f.box (Box 1)
- Academic Career, 1953-1995; 2
  - Yale University, 1
    - Black Student Alliance, Yale related material, 1964-1980; 1 Cubic Feet 1 c.f. box (Box 2)
    - Yale University related material, 1953-1993; 1 Cubic Feet 1 c. f. box (Box 3)
  - State University of New York, 2
    - Academic career, 1969-1982; 1 Cubic Feet 1 c.f. box. (Box 4)
  - University of California at Los Angeles and the University of Rochester, New York, 3
  - University of Virginia, 4
    - Academic career; Topical files, 1968-1995; 1 Cubic Feet 1 c.f. box. (Box 5)
- Topical Files, 1950-2009; 3
  - Topical files, 1966-2000; 1 Cubic Feet 1 c.f. box. (Box 6)
  - Topical files, 1950-1994; 1 Cubic Feet 1 c.f. box. (Box 7)
  - Topical files, 1969-1992; 1 Cubic Feet 1 c.f. box. (Box 8)
  - Topical files, 1969-1994; 1 Cubic Feet 1 c.f. box. (Box 9)
  - Topical files, 1861-2009; 1 Cubic Feet 1 c.f. box. (Box 10)
- Research Materials, 4
  - Topical files; Research material, 1937-1994; 1 Cubic Feet 1 c.f. box. (Box 11)
  - Research material, 1860's-1995; 1 Cubic Feet 1 c.f. box. (Box 12)
  - Research material, 1817-1993; 1 Cubic Feet 1 c.f. box. (Box 13)
  - Research material, 1863-1992; 1 Cubic Feet 1 c.f. box (Box 14)
  - Research material, circa 1968-1969; 1 Cubic Feet 1 c.f. box. (Box 15)
    Scope and Contents
    Armistead L. Robinson, Scholar of the House Thesis, Yale University, "In the Aftermath of Slavery: Blacks and Reconstruction in Memphis, Tennessee, 1865-1870": Research note cards (5x8 multicolored-lined):"Pre 1865, 1865, 1866, 1867, 1868, 1869, 1866 (again), Not yet Filed, 1870 (2)"
  - Research material, circa 1968-1969; 1 Cubic Feet 1 c.f. box. (Box 16)
    Armistead L. Robinson, Scholar of the House Thesis, Yale University, "In the Aftermath of Slavery: Blacks and Reconstruction in Memphis, Tennessee, 1865-1870": Research note cards (5x8 multicolored-lined):"1865, 1866 (2), 1867, 1869, 1865, 1866, 1867, 1868, 1869 (again), 1870 (2), Not Yet Filed, 1865, 1867, 1868, 1869, 1870, Not Yet Filed, 1865, 1866,1867, 1868,1869,1870, Not Yet Filed, 1865,1866, 1867, 1868, 1869, 1870 Not Yet Filed, 1865, 1866, General Patterns, A-W"
  - Research material, circa 1969-1977; 1 Cubic Feet 1 c.f. box. (Box 17)
    Armistead L. Robinson dissertation, University of Rochester, "Day of Jubilo: The Civil War and the Demise of Slavery in the Mississippi Valley, 1861-1865": Bibliographic note cards (5x8 white-lined): "A-W and unrelated miscellaneous note cards
  - Research material, circa 1969-1977; 1 Cubic Feet 1 c.f. box. (Box 18)
    Armistead L. Robinson dissertation, University of Rochester, "Day of Jubilo: The Civil War and the Demise of Slavery in the Mississippi Valley, 1861-1865": Bibliographic note cards (5x8 white-lined): "Maps, Official Documents, Government Documents: Federal, Guides to Manuscript Collections, Guide to Printed Materials, Special Collections, Printed Public Documents, Miscellaneous Documents, Newspapers (4), Urban Directories and State Gazetteers, Periodicals, Personal Collections, Published Letters and Papers, Printed Correspondence, Memoirs, and Autobiographies, Diaries and Journals, Memoirs and Contemporary Accounts, Contemporary Periodicals, Contemporary Books and Pamhlets (2)" and "Regional and State Slavery Studies"
  - Research material, circa 1969-1977; 1 Cubic Feet 1 c.f. box. (Box 19)
    Armistead L. Robinson dissertation, University of Rochester, "Day of Jubilo: The Civil War and the Demise of Slavery in the Mississippi Valley, 1861-1865": Bibliographic note cards (5x8 white-lined): "Works Dealing Chiefly With the South, Biography, Biographical Studies, Agriculture, Manufacturing, Commerce, and Transportation, The Southern Frontier, Biography, Biographies, Articles in Periodicals and Publications, General American History, State and Local History, Politics, Political and Social Change, Miltary Studies, General and Special Histories, American History: Special Topics, The Wilkinson-Burr Intrigues"
  - Census Material, 1850-1880, 1976-1985; 1 Cubic Feet 1 c. f. box. (Box 20)
  - Census material, 1850-1978; 1 Cubic Feet 1 c.f. box. (Box 21)
  - Census material, 1850-1860, 1975; 1 Cubic Feet 1 c.f. box. (Box 22)
  - Census material, 1850-1880, 1975; 1 Cubic Feet 1 c.f. box. (Box 23)
  - Census material, 1860-1888; 1 Cubic Feet 1 c.f. box. (Box 24)
  - Census material, 1860-1880, 1976; 1 Cubic Feet 1 c.f. box. (Box 25)
  - Census material, 1880; 1 Cubic Feet 1 c.f. box. (Box 26)
  - Census material, 1880; 1 Cubic Feet 1 c.f. box. (Box 27)
  - Census material, 1880; 1 Cubic Feet 1 c.f. box. (Box 28)
  - Census material, 1979; 1 Cubic Feet 1 c.f. box. (Box 29)
  - Census material, 1978-1979; 1 Cubic Feet 1 c.f. box. (Box 30)
  - Census material, 1978-1979; 1 Cubic Feet 1 c.f. box. (Box 31)
  - Census material; Writings & Publications, 1978-1991; 1 Cubic Feet 1 c.f. box. (Box 32)
- Writings and Publications, 1966-2001; 5
  - Bitter Fruits of Bondage material, 1979-1982; 1 Cubic Feet 1 c.f. box. (Box 33)
  - Bitter Fruits of Bondage material, 1982-1985; 1 Cubic Feet 1 c.f. box. (Box 34)
  - Bitter Fruits of Bondage material, 1984-1999; 1 Cubic Feet 1 c.f. box. (Box 35)
  - Bitter Fruits of Bondage material, 1999-2001; 1 Cubic Feet 1 c.f. box. (Box 36)
  - Bitter Fruits of Bondage, 1976-1999; 1 Cubic Feet 1 c. f. box. (Box 37)
  - Writing drafts, 1968-1995; 1 Cubic Feet 1 c.f. box. (Box 38)
  - Writing drafts, 1974-1976; 1 Cubic Feet 1 c.f. box. (Box 39)
  - Various writing and publications, 1976-1995; 1 Cubic Feet 1 c.f. box. (Box 40)
  - Drafts and miscellaneous material, 1969-1995; 1 Cubic Feet 1 c.f. box. (Box 41)
  - Drafts and miscellaneous material, 1966-1994; 1 Cubic Feet 1 c.f. box. (Box 42)
- Oversize Material, 6
  - Oversize materials (Box U-10)
    - James Seddon, Secretary of War, to Jefferson Davis, President, C. S. A. [photostatic copy pages 302-319, stamped "War Record Copied 1861-1865"], circa 1863 January 3
    - "Battlefields of the Civil War with Descriptive Notes/Compiled and Drawn in the Cartographic Division of the National Geographic Society for The National Geographic Magazine, Melville Bell Grosvenor, Editor; James M. Darley, Chief Cartographer" [On verso: 10 detail maps], 1961 April
    - Office of Black Affairs of the University of Louisville presents Black Studies and Afro-American History Conference, March 23, 24, 25: Louisville, Kentucky with Armstead Robinson as "Editor, Yale Law Review" among the speakers (two yellow posters) [related folder in Box 7], circa 1970 March
    - Certificate of Recognition/Given for outstanding contributions by administrators, faculty, staff and students of African descent at the University of California at Los Angeles presented to Armstead Robinson, 1978 June
    - Armstead Robinson/Professor of History, University of California at Los Angeles: From Dred Scott to Benign Neglect–U. S. Civil Rights/The Afro-American Experience, sponsored by a grant from the National Endowment for the Humanities [related folder in Box 4], circa 1979 May 1
    - Carter G. Woodson, pencil sketch [related folder in Box 7], 1982 January 26
    - Carter G. Woodson, pencil and ink sketch [related folder in Box 7], 1982 January 26
    - Corporate/Community Schools of America (C/CSA): "Thank you for helping us grow... Smarter! Corporate/Community Schools of America December, 1989" (color photograph) [related folders in Boxes 8 and 9], 1989 December
    - Virginia State Library Board resolution of thanks to Armstead L. Robinson for his service [related folders in Box 11], 1990 January
    - Fall 1991/Monday Noon Series/A Free Cultural Series/University of Missouri-At. Louis: October 21/Academic Culture and Scientific Racism: The Case of Charles Wesley, Pioneer Historian of the Confederacy"/Armstead L. Robinson/Director, Carter G. Woodson Institute for Afro-American and African Studies/University of Virginia/Will be held in 222 J. C. Penney
    - Certificate declaring Armstead Robinson a Honorary Citizen of Natchez, Mississippi, 1994 January 18
    - Booker T. Washington National Monument (BOWA): Wayside Exhibit Plan w/cover letter from Michelle Jacques [related folders in Box 8], 1995 January
    - LeRoi Jones: An evening with LeRoi Jones and his Spirit House Repertory Theatre (Yale University), undated
    - "Images of Afro-Americans of the Emancipation Era": incomplete numbered set of black and white reprints from Harper's Magazine, Leslie's Illustrated, Currier & Ives: Hodges Publications, Liverpool, New York, with 22 page commentary [Note: Prints 5, 21, 22, 23, 24, and 25 are missing.], undated
      1. The Emancipation of the Negroes, January, 1863 [January 24, 1863] 2. Colored Troops, Under General Wild, Liberating Slaves in North Carolina [January 23, 1864] 3. A Negro Regiment In Action [March 14, 1863] 4. The Negro In The War–Various Employments of The Colored Men in The Federal Army [undated] 6. Negroes Escaping Out of Slavery [May 7, 1864] 7. Plantation Police, or Home Guard, Examining Passes on the Road Leading to the Levee of the Mississippi River [May 11, 1863] 8. Emancipated Slaves, White and Colored [January 20, 1864] 9. President Lincoln Riding Through Richmond, April 4, 1865, Immediately After The Evacuation of The City By General Lee [undated] 10. The First Vote [November 16, 1867] 11. The First Colored Senator and Representatives [undated] 12. A Remarkable Event in the History of the National Congress–The Honorable John Willis Menard, Colored Representative From Louisiana, Receiving the Congratulations of His Friends On The Floor of the House, Dec. 7th, 1868 [undated] 13. Flower Sellers In The Market at Washington, D. C./Free Municipal Election in Richmond Since the End of The War–Registration of Colored Voters [June 4, 1870] 14. Celebration of the Abolition of Slavery in the District of Columbia by the Colored People, in Washington, April 19, 1866/A Political discussion [May 12, 1866] 15. Educating the Freedmen/St. Philip's Church, Richmond, Virginia–School For Colored Children [May 25, 1867] 16. Zion School For Colored Children, Charleston, South Carolina [December 15, 1866] 17. Cotton Team In North Carolina [May 12, 1866] 18. Our Cotton Campaign in South Carolina–Gathering, Picking and Shipping The Cotton Crops of The Sea Islands, Port Royal By The Federal Army, Under General Sherman [February 15, 1862] 19. Rice Culture on the Ogeechee, Near Savannah [January 5, 1867] 20. Cotton Culture In The South [n. d.]
    - University of North Carolina Department of Geography template, 1790-1860, undated
      37 maps.
    - "Topographical Map of Memphis and Vicinity Surveyed and drawn by order of Maj. Gen. W. T. Sherman by Lieuts. Pitzman & Frick Topographical Engineers," Copy from The National Archives Record Group No. 77, T-125-1 (positive photostatic copy), undated
    - "Topographical Map of Memphis and Vicinity Surveyed and drawn by order of Maj. Gen. W. T. Sherman by Lieuts. Pitzman & Frick Topographical Engineers," Copy from The National Archives Record Group No. 77, T-125-1 (negative photostatic copy), undated
    - "General Topographical Map Sheet XIV-XXCopy from The National Archives Record Group No. 94, Civil War Atlas Plates 149, 150, 153, 154, and 155" (positive and negative photostatic copies), undated
      The ten maps in this group were reprinted in George B. Davis, Leslie J. Perry, Joseph W. Kirkley; compiled by Calvin D. Cowles, The Official Military Atlas of the Civil War, with an Introduction by Richard Sommers (New York: The Fairfax Press, 1983) [other publishers: New York: Gramercy Books; Avenel, N. J.: distributed by Outlook Book Company, 1983]